you
Welcome to the lighter side of the
spectrum, a podcast where we explore how
to find
joy, connection and growth while
navigating the challenges of parenting
kids and
teens on the autism spectrum. Remember
that inclusion and hope are key to making
life better for everyone and that even in
the most challenging moments, there's
always a lighter side. Now here's your
host, David Kaufer.
Hey everyone, welcome to another episode
of the lighter side of the spectrum. Glad
you can join us. I am so excited today
because I have a good friend and a very
knowledgeable guest, Andrew Millevojvich.
Did I get it? Did I get it, Andrew? You
nailed it. All right. All that practice
paid off. But let me give you a little
intro
to Andrew. He provided this and I'm going
to spice it up because I do that in
marketing. But Andrew is...
husband to an awesome wife and father of
two great young adults, an engineer and
statistician that consults with academia
and industry in experimental development.
And he's a co-author to Quality by
Experimental Design, which is published by
Taylor
and Francis. I wanted to add, like I said,
he's a great resource. He's a part of our
spelling and autism community, but he's
also the lead developer and designer and a
Don't know what the official title is,
Andrew, but that's cool app that was used
in
that important research project at
University of Virginia that I want to talk
about
in a little bit. welcome Andrew. Thanks.
for joining me. Hey, thank you for
inviting
me. I'm really stoked and glad to be here
today. So one of the things that we talk
about, like I said, it's the lighter side
of the spectrum, but you know, we were
autism dads, right? And there's something
unique about
being in that club and it certainly is a
club and a fraternity in many ways. But
yeah, I think it's helpful to kind of get
a little background information. If you
could kind of tell me briefly about your
journey and your son is Nicholas, right?
And just why you can't tell us a little
bit about how old was he when he was
diagnosed and kind of like, were those
early years like? Well, he was, he was
very
young, like up until about
six months, all the developmental
milestones were there. But then there was
a period
where after nine months, ten months, we
start noticing him hand flapping a lot,
doing things while in a seated position,
which we later on, it gets a label called
stimming, not knowing that's what you
should give it.
Flapping, they call it flapping. Exactly.
And delayed walking and whatnot. And I
remember actually being at my ear and nose
doctor, his office, and they had this
little pad of paper. And prior to this, by
the way, I should say we went into our
family doctor and we said, this just looks
unusual. And he must be about 12 months
by this time.
And, he had a bit of a rough journey and w
within a month of, being born, had
developed RSV, had to be intubated. So he,
days of life were quite rough. Yeah. But
got through that thankfully and
everything. And then, the doctor basically
said, oh,
he's observing the stimming and says, oh,
he's a naturally excitable kid. Don't
worry about it.
And then when I was at the ear and nose
throat specialist, saw this information
flyer talking about autism and some of the
symptoms. That's when it started gluing
in. You started kind of doing like a
mental check, like you're kind of like
check,
Absolutely. And I'm like, hey, my wife,
Antoinette, but you know, like delayed
speech, the stimming and all that kind of
stuff.
And so we got referred to a developmental
pediatrician and by 18 months we had the
diagnosis of autism. then everything after
that was history, right? What can we do
to best support our child? Yeah. So it's
been a long, it's been a long journey. You
caught it early on. then again, you kind
of started doing all the things that,
we're
told to do, right? Like early intervention
and how important that is, which
obviously it is.
And then so, kind of go through it then
education. What did they, you so, and I
just
want to note, so you're actually in the
Toronto and the, was, you live in Toronto
now, right? The Toronto area. Right. Yeah.
So this is all, so yeah, so experience
might be slightly different, in terms of
resources and experience in Canada versus
kind of what we do here in the States.
well, I would say they're quite similar.
Back in the day, was like, how do we get
our kid into ABA therapy as much as quick
and fast as possible, right? And that's
what we did. We sought out the
psychologists
that were experienced in autism, put a
program together for our kid. Where I
think
our family's experiences maybe deviated a
little bit was...
By training, I'm a researcher. So I will
do a literature search for all kinds of
papers on autism, and I would do extensive
readings. And then I'd find out what the
best evidence was out there that suggested
a type of therapy would be beneficial.
And we would just start and try and do
things.
that would be, would be helpful. And, a
lot of it today explains, where our son is
today. how so? Yeah. When you think about,
people will talk about, casein and gluten
free diets and, I go beyond that. like why
are certain diets recommended and.
And what you end up finding, and the
literature is getting up to speed in this
point
here where they talk about the gut brain
act. And digestion is a really, important
concept for our kids. And they often
experience constipation issues and a
variety of
other issues. And at the end of the day,
Can you make it easier for them to digest
food? Yeah. And what you find is foods
come in all different kinds of molecular
structures that have to get broken down
and
then digested. Well, at the end of the
day, if you can give a diet to your kid
that
consumes the... doesn't have to spend so
much time digesting, then they can absorb
more nutrients more effectively. So case
in point in me, if I eat a pay to...
plate of pasta, my body will be so busy
digesting, I'll go to sleep because
there's
no energy. So when you look at our son
right now, I mean, I wish I had his
physique,
but he looks like an Olympic swimmer. then
that kind of is philosophically, you
can't cure the autism, at least there's no
cure for it. And should there even be
one, right?
some of the symptoms, you said, in terms
of, yeah, I don't mean to interrupt. was
going back because I really love the way
you described the injury. was going to
say,
I wish I had, I wish doctors who described
it that well back when Stone was young
and experienced knowing what we know now,
experiencing constipation pain, right?
Like a lot of these things, like I said,
it makes sense if you can digest and the
reasons behind why do our kids have these
issues. That's kind of like.
a different topic, but just understanding
and that, because I think, I don't know, I
don't know what the thinking is today. I
know again, back when Stone was young, so
we're looking about what, 10 to probably
12, 13 years ago when again, I first kind
of discovered diet and learning about that
from naturopaths and research and my
limited research. It was kind of just kind
of revolutionary. And like it just, was,
and there were a lot, a lot of skeptics,
right? remember.
kind of scoring this appointment at one of
the leading local pediatricians here.
guy's supposed to be like, one of the
nation's top experts in autism. And I got
an
appointment with him when I guess it's
still, was probably three or four. We had
just kind of started, the gluten free case
and free diet. We're talking, he,
literally just stopped. He's just like,
Well, if you think that's going to help,
okay, whatever. Wow. I've heard in his
sense, changed his tune. Fortunately he's
seen enough kiddos and all, but anyway,
the point being like, think that there
were skeptics. don't know if there are
still
as many skeptics, if it's more accepted
today that this is like a real issue.
Yeah.
Oh no, it is. And, I think it highlights
one of the issues, about autism because
When you try to look for issues that are
unrelated, let's say, to autism, it's very
easy to use that label and brush it off
and say, oh, it's the autism. And then you
ignore the other health issues because
you're trying to explain it away as the
autism, right? And a lot of these kids of
ours, they have other underlying issues.
The one today that stands out, which is my
leads into my tip of the day is just the
whole movement and developmental
coordination that since 2015 now is being
recognized as a core symptom of autism and
that's motor impairment. And I could talk
about that for ad infinitum and why that's
very important to address and something
that doesn't get taken into consideration
these days.
with, a lot of our, with, a lot of our
kids. Yeah, that's a really good point.
And I
think in a lot of ways, kind of like some
motor development, the role of motor, the
role of the praxia, all of those related
issues are kind of still at the early
stages in terms of, acceptance and
acknowledgement, right? The DSM, which is
the
standard that doctors all use for
diagnosing certain things. I believe the
2013 version finally acknowledged that you
can have developmental coordination
disorder co-occurring with autism, which
is just
the medical way of saying dyspraxia. then
I don't have to tell you about the
wonderful work that Elizabeth Torres has
done out of Rutgers University.
that has shown there's an impairment in
motor learning in our autistic kids. And
that is so important to understand because
once you clue into it and realize it's an
impairment, you can figure out how to
address it and really improve the quality
of
life for our kids so that they can
experience things that they otherwise
would never
have had.
to experience. can give you a perfect
example of that. Yeah, I love examples. I
love
stories. Well, when you think of it, when
you look at motor impairment and autism,
the research that Dr. Torres has shown is
that these movements, when you're a
typical people like you and I, we learn
how to make the future movement more
efficient based on our prior movements.
So when we learn to pick up a glass of
water, for example, my hand might come on
the
top of it, my hand might slide down the
side, my first experience is with that
glass. And then when I learn what grip is
comfortable and what makes it easier to
lift and drink, then the future movement
emulates that. mechanism in autism is
impaired.
and the impairment increases as the
diagnosis of autism increases in severity
as
measured on an ADOS. So it means that this
kinematic learning in autism gets
impaired. And this is the epiphany for me.
Right? Imagine what happens to social
skills because as you age with your peer
group and instead of...
sitting in a circle, talking about a book
and rolling a ball around when you're a
toddler. Now you're playing soccer where
the level of kinematic skill in gross
motor
and five motor is far more higher as age
or the demand is so much higher as age
increases that our kiddos fall behind. And
then that impacts their social
experiences. So, that's a great, that's a
great point. And to be clear too, also, I
just want to add again for
for listeners who aren't as familiar about
this. Again, this has nothing to do with
cognitive abilities, is sometimes, right.
This is, but this is the mistake that, so
many make, right. Is that because there's
this disconnect in terms of the motor
though, that, does impair other areas in
terms of communication and some of these
motor abilities, but they've been fused
together to say, oh, well they're just.
developmentally disabled. You think about
every, that touches on an interesting
study by a psychologist out in Montreal
who studied 40 autistic people. When you
look at every test you can do to measure,
collect or whatever, it depends on motor
skills. Right. Everyone, like every test.
If the motor skills are impaired,
then how do you expect to get an exact...
accurate results of the person's
intelligence? It's difficult. So you have
to do things differently. And I wish
today's academia field would recognize it
because they were faced with this problem
in the 1930s and they solved it.
And I don't know if you're aware of this,
David, but when you were coming into the
United States at the start of the
industrial revolution, you needed labor.
Right.
Well, a lot of these people couldn't speak
English. So how would you test them in
the English language to know whether or
not they had the intellect to do certain
types of jobs? Well, you had to, you had
to invent a different test that wasn't
based on language. Oh, wow.
And so those are called your Raven's
progressive matrices. And they've been
around
since the 1930s. And so this researcher,
when she did that for these group of
children that had impaired motor ability,
which they couldn't control the fine motor
muscles in their mouth to speak. They
found that they lost their, intellectual
disability diagnosis. And so why aren't we
using those more? Well, I don't know.
Honestly, don't know Is it just testing
bias or is it just one of those situations
where the system's used to using these
other standardized tests? Yes, and that's
the
thing because the community is, when I
mean the community, the people that want
to
do these assessments want to know if the
tests have been normed against the certain
population, right? So that you can compare
normative...
values to the population to see where
things are. So when you invent these new
tests
and you trial them on just a few people,
you got to push hundreds of subjects
through this area. So you'll often hear
the term autism is very heterogeneous,
right? So one of the things that prevents
us doing this in the area of autism is how
do you partition
autistic people in different buckets, like
maybe this group are, have some speaking
ability and this group doesn't. And
because the group is so heterogeneous,
they
don't know how to create the
subpopulations to do these normative
tests. Right. So
it gets very, difficult. And that's why
they don't do it.
But that kind of goes into the study out
of the University of Virginia and the
innovative things we needed to do to test
literacy, for example, right? And I like
to say autism doesn't care what your
education is. Right. If you have a PhD in
education and the person with autism has a
neurological issue,
that impairs the circuitry in the brain
that impacts motor. Well, then I should be
talking to a neuroscientist, right? And so
you need a very diversified team of
healthcare professionals, which thankfully
here in Canada with our son, I mean,
we've got a fantastic medical team from
neurologists to neuroscientists to...
developmental pediatricians and
ophthalmologists and all kinds of things
to support
our kids. That's what they all need,
right? They do. And like you said, we've
talked
about, that fortunately you do have that
team. Unfortunately, you've been in a
position that you've been able to build
that team and support that team.
Unfortunately, especially here in the U.S.
where the health care system in general,
again, isn't as supportive, we'll say.
I think that's really hard for a lot of
people to try to build that kind of a team
anyway. is and even in Canada, don't get
me wrong, we have our issues up here. The
parent really has to be, for lack of a
better word, pushy and not take no for an
answer. think that's universal, Andrew. I
think we've learned that, right? that.
and again, that's, that is kind of one of
the pieces of advice I'm always giving
when asked or even when I'm not asked.
It's just, especially for parents and
younger
kids who again, who've either just gotten
the diagnosis or starting school. I'm just
like, you gotta be pushy. Like you said,
you gotta push because you're the
advocate.
Like you're the one who's going to have to
make this happen because others won't.
They're going to do what they need to do.
Whether it's the school system doing the
bare minimum as you and I have both.
at both experience. hope you're enjoying
the lighter side of the spectrum. So far
we're commercial free, but if you're
finding value here, one way to support the
show
is by considering me for speaking
engagement. I speak on unlocking
potential,
whether it's for individuals like my son
or for entire organizations. I also offer
fractional CMO services for businesses
needing strategic marketing support
without
the full-time commitment, drawing on over
35 years of experience in marketing.
My agency has helped companies and
healthcare practices increase their value,
grow,
and even prepare for acquisition. To learn
more about my speaking topics, visit
davidkoffer.com. Or if you're interested
in our marketing or fractional CMO
services, check out kofermarketing.com. If
you're enjoying this episode, please
leave a review. Your feedback means a lot
and it helps me make this podcast even
more useful. Lastly, don't forget to share
it with anyone who would appreciate the
insights and stories we're sharing here.
Thanks again for listening.
All of this stuff that I've just mentioned
about motor impairment. mean, what's the
underlying good message out of all of that
stuff, right? And, in the case of our
son, was like, well, it's winter. I don't
want to be indoors all day. I wonder if he
can learn how to ski. Now, right away,
others will say, well, he's got autism.
There's no way we're going to be able to
come down a hill. Well, my son's been
doing
it now for seven years. We just found a
great program.
called track three and it's a disability.
It's a program to support kids with
disabilities to learn how to ski. And so
they pair you up with a couple of ski
instructors and they start on a bunny hill
and they teach you how to ski. Now my son
goes to Glen Eden at the top of a, after
years on a bunny hill, he was
going on the big hill and doing all his
best, S's all the way down the hill,
right?
I love the videos. I remember you sharing
them last, winter, right? Oh yeah,
absolutely. I mean, I'm at the bottom. I'm
just rooting him like crazy. I'm happy as
heck seeing that he can do something that
otherwise he wouldn't have had a chance at
doing because nobody would presume the
competence, right? Those programs are
gold.
We're lucky enough to have something
similar here in the Seattle area, which is
called Outdoors for All.
Right. And they do that like it's a
skiing. Yeah. And they do a ski program.
has
participated in that previously. It's been
a few years. He wants to do it again. So
we're planning on doing that. They do
cycling, a lot of those things, right?
They're
just wonderful programs for, kids to give
them those, give them those opportunities,
like you said. Yeah. Absolutely. So like I
said, we'd like to have that little
feature for the tip of the week. You kind
of touched on it a little bit earlier. So
let's go ahead.
Let's see if producer Dave is ready for
the intro.
All right. How's that for intro Absolutely
love it. It's great. so what you got for
us? Well, it's presumed competence and I,
and I say that broadly. but you know, as
your kids age, you don't want them to be
withheld from activities that everybody
else can, participate in. So first get
over that hurdle and assume they can do
it.
and then find the program that suits their
motor needs to actually be able to enjoy
that program. Like cycling, for example. I
remember my son could ride a two-wheeler,
but then turning was a bit of a hassle and
then he'd get dejected. Well, guess what?
bought it. I got a tri-bite bent. Now he
can ride everything. can cruise around,
right? Those are awesome. Do things and...
Next year, we're going to get a tandem
bike and we're going to cruise together
because at my age, I got to get exercise
and do some of that kind of stuff. And so
get them into those activities that get
them to not only engage in those
activities
other people do, but that gives them an
opportunity to also socialize. Right. I
haven't found an autistic person that
hasn't been in a social environment and
have a
sad face on. Right.
And so I think get out there and assume
they enjoy those activities and just are
taken well Yeah, and again, I was just
gonna say that's another great point you
make
Andrew again in terms of social activities
again I think that one of the false
narratives that we had heard for so many
years and I even again I understood this
was stone when he was younger as people
are like, oh, they're just not social
Autistic people aren't social. I'm like,
well, how social would you be if you can't
talk like?
How social would you be if I dropped you
in the middle of Beijing tomorrow and
said,
go, why don't you go hang out with these
people? You wouldn't want to do that.
wouldn't know what the heck they're
saying. You wouldn't be able to, or maybe
you
would figure it out quickly, but you
couldn't pick up the language. It's just,
again, this, assumption, this societal
bias, right? I've got a great example of
that. were at a picnic and there were,
there was a soccer pitch there.
And Nicholas was a teenager at this time,
or maybe pre-teenager. And there was a
group of kids playing soccer. And our son
was just sitting on the bench. All of a
sudden, he gets up and he walks right into
the middle of that group.
And everybody's like, well, Nicholas, get
out of the way or get on the bench. And I
come back and I'm like, no, He got up and
he came in this group for a reason. Yeah.
And I'm telling you that reason is he
wants to participate. Don't tell me he's
not
wanting to be sold. Right. That's
inclusion right there. It's the motor
that's
preventing him from kicking or passing a
ball. So guess what the group does? They
adapt.
And they start passing him the ball and he
stays at the center and he starts passing
it to everybody else. And while he's doing
that, he's cracking the biggest smile on
his face. those moments. is awesome.
Right. Oh, absolutely. Yeah, absolutely.
So
like I mentioned earlier, so we kind of
met through the spelling community, right?
And so you've, been part of that journey
and we've shared lots of stories. But one
of the things I think is really cool is
what you're doing.
with Nicholas as an author. He's a book
author, right? He's published multiple
books
now. Talk about that. Yeah, he's got the
third one and the coloring. He had this
idea for a coloring book. Oh, I don't
think I'd heard about that. he wrote his
first
book was... So he wrote a series on
Detective Nick and the first book was
called
Detective Nick.
case of the missing belly buttons. mean,
right there, come up with a title. I love
it. then the next one was Detective Nick,
where did Mr. Creatures' cows go? And talk
about the presumption of competence. It's
a story about cows that appreciate reading
Shakespeare and can talk, but nobody
believes them.
Oh wow. Perfect. And they all want to go
to the Howledge.
I mean, how he comes up with this stuff,
make a poignant societal point just throws
me. And then the other one just recently
this year was Detective Nick and the case,
the mysterious case of the interstellar
beings. And so he's quite the little short
kid's writer, which
The story behind that is actually amazing.
don't know if you've ever read the Robert
Munch. Robert Munch is like probably the
greatest selling children's author. the
first book that he wrote was, Oh God, Love
You Much or something about how the
mother takes care of the child. And then
when the mother becomes elderly, the child
then takes care of the mother.
And I'm sorry if I'm not remembering the
title, but yeah, he was an American who
happens to now live in Guelph, Ontario,
which is the city not too far from where
we
live. And so Nicholas loved his books and
he said, well, I want to be an author. I
want to write some books. like, how do we,
do you think we can ask Robert Munch? And
I'm like, well, let's.
I guess so. says, yeah, like, why don't we
just send them a letter, dad? And so we
did. And he responded. Oh, cool. So it was
all that's correct. And that was the
motivation to, this wonderful gentleman
just sent the kind letter encouraging him
to
go forward and gave them all kinds of tips
on how to get the book out there and
whatnot. that's how we ended up here
today. Right.
Yeah. You may have told me this before,
Andrew, but how, what was Nicholas's level
of communication before spelling, before
he was introduced to the spelling
methodology? is he reliable at all? he
have speak, how much speak? No, he, was,
he
was non-speaking. Yeah. I mean, he had
words here and there. And when he was
upset
and he really wanted to communicate what
he want, he could string out two or three
words.
But he was using sign language for period
of a time. so it never went further. I
wouldn't say because of Nicholas. It was
very difficult for my wife and I to learn
it because at the time, if you're an
autistic parent,
and you don't have funding sources and
you're trying to get all this ABA help for
your kids and just get them all the
supports that they need. You're, paying
for this
out of pocket. I remember you're paying
for it. Plus the time, right? Like, that's
the thing. There's like bandwidth.
remember it. Sorry. I just like, cause I
remember
people saying that to me are asking us
that again, when Stone was young, they're
like, well, why don't you try, why don't
you just try learning sign language?
And I'm like, we're fricking drowning
here. right. mean, there's, the very much
that
survival element, right? Okay. We're,
focusing on the lighter side, of course,
which
we want to do, but the reality is that,
man, it's just, you're, we're working,
we're
working all the time. You said trying
different therapies and.
And then me and just still trying to be a
parent, like I said, and then you have
another son that you're parenting as Stone
as a twin brother. Like, there's only so
much that you can do also, I think, which
plays into it. Yeah. absolutely. And
that's why often, and I think I might've
even used this term with you, do you have
the privilege of time? Right. And, it is a
privilege without a doubt. Yeah, for
sure. Absolutely.
All right. So this, is a good lead and
because we're talking about family and
stresses and things like that. And then
again, something we've talked about. So
let's go. This is for this is our fact or
fiction autism factor fiction segment. All
right. See if, see if we have an intro for
that. Get quick time ready. And here we
go. This is autism factor fiction. We're
breaking down what's real, what's rumor
and
what might surprise you. Let's go. So,
That's that we're going to call her
Sabrina. Just I'm going to steal that from
producer. Yeah. This is podcast. She's
she, he loaned her out to us from chat
GPT.
But so for factor fiction, autism factor
fiction, one of the things I remember
hearing early on was that, I've been
looking at if I have a great supportive
wife,
we've been married 27 years. I know you in
similar situation, but I don't know yet.
You always hear that the divorce rate is
higher among couples with autistic.
kids or special needs kids. yeah, that's
true. So you're okay. So you're going with
fact. Yeah, I'm going with fact. Okay. So
at least again, according to, or AI, I
hope I'm wrong. Yeah. So, well, okay. So
the belief in divorce rates are higher
among couples with autistic children is
largely a myth.
Research in the past decade has shown that
while parenting a child with autism does
bring unique stressors, these couples do
not have a significantly higher divorce
rate compared to parents with neurotypical
children. As a matter of fact, a 2010
study from the Journal of Autism and
Developmental Disorders found that while
parents of autistic children face distinct
challenges, their marriages are no more
likely to end in divorce than other
marriages. In fact, some studies even
indicate
the couples raising children with autism.
may experience a stronger sense of
partnership and shared purpose, which can
have a
stabilizing effect on the relationship. it
can strain relationships. I love that
last part you just said, because when I
think about my wife, we are such a tag
team.
don't know what we would do without each
other, right? Because that's how we make
it
work, right?
So I totally believe in that because that
shows up in our marriage. Yeah. think,
yeah, same here. It's, a divide and
conquer, right? It's a partnership. It's
you
have to do, I think it's really kind of
the only way you make it work. And it
requires that level of commitment to the
relationship, to the family, to really, to
really see that through. So I thought that
was really kind of interesting, right?
Cause
I remember when I said early on, was like,
okay, as if we didn't have to worry about
you're getting like these messages like,
well, good luck with that marriage now.
Well, you know what? This is one of the,
when I'm being tested, I like to be right,
but this is the first time I'm really glad
I'm wrong. Yeah. Well, like I said, it's,
again, a message of hope for, like I said,
the other parents out there, right? Who
are, who may be challenging.
so like we were joking about this before
we started, we, there's so much more to
talk about. and I want to get into like,
so there's going to be a part two or part
three for sure. We'll bring you back. But
one of the things we talked about spelling
and I've touched upon this, I'm always
going to be talking about it in each of my
podcasts because it's just, incredible
journey with stone. But I thought you had
a
really interesting observe observation
about how kind of comparing the stages of
spelling for parents.
How similar to startups in a way, like, so
you talked about what the storming
forming and norming, right? Yeah. Can you
talk about that a little bit and just kind
of, again, how, you've seen that kind of
play out, maybe in your own experience,
but
also again, you've, talked to and become
friends with a lot of other families.
Well,
once you, go down this path and you
realize the world can open up.
And what communication actually does for
you, feel this kind of euphoria. is great.
And so it's a natural high. But then as
time goes on, it's like, okay, how am I
going to sustain this? We need more
training. We got to develop the motor
skills.
There's a kinematic learning process.
there is so much more that we need to do
to now maintain this thing. Education,
right? Like catching up on education.
mean, that's another, yeah. There's all of
that stuff. so, and then even generalizing
to other people and giving the speller an
opportunity to interact and work with
other people that know how to use the
methodologies and whatnot to support the
needs of the speller.
and then you get to this, maturity point,
it would kind of hit home for us where I
just turned 60, and, my wife, I'm not
going to say what her age is because if
she
finds out, she'll, but, what happens when
we're not here?
They're going to live on, they're going to
keep on going. And so now the challenge
is how to get them the motor support they
need to get to a point of some reliable
way of independence so that they don't
have to depend on other people. Because
then
it turns into that privilege of time. We
can afford the time now and give our son
whatever he needs. But now we're thinking
about that next stage in life because I
I could run around the block, it wouldn't
be an issue. Now walking is getting,
you're feeling the age. You know what I
mean? Like your son's an adult, you're
getting to be a senior. You can tell by
the color of my head, it's white. I've
been
there for a while. And so you're slowing
down. I like to take naps in the
afternoon.
Right? Yeah. So changed. So yeah, we
change and we can't keep up with these
kids. So
how do you give them that level of support
when they're in their prime and you're
not, right? So.
That's some of the stuff that everybody is
going to go through and, experience. And
it's just like everything else. Right.
Yeah. Like it's just, it's just different
stages. Right. And like I said, I thought
it was just a really keen observation
because like I said, it's similar again,
what we went through it later. And I think
that's the perfect word. again, it's
euphoria, right? Like there's just
nothing,
like that. the first time spent the first
time they're communicating, like we
hitting those milestones when they, well,
you, for what really
bothers me is how autistic people are
emotionally treated. Right. When you
interact
with another person through this unique
mode of communication called speech and
you
can show your facial features and show the
emotions you're feeling and how that
resonates with another person, if autistic
folks aren't showing those emotions. That
doesn't mean they don't have them. But
then what it means is the reciprocating
person develops a mindset of that person
and
then preaches them more. I don't want to
say as a person just standing there in an
inanimate object, but the level of
emotional appreciation is not there that
would be
with the neuro-typical people.
And this is what this beautiful form of
communication provides. It enhances love.
Right? Yeah, it sure does. And so much of
that is missing from our society today.
mean, so much of what we see in the news
is just, you know, yeah, lot of
divisiveness, lot of... Yeah, absolutely.
And this is why I love autistic parents,
because for me,
A measure of love is the amount of time
and sacrifice and effort that people give
of
themselves to other people. I mean,
there's only one reason why you do that.
You
love your kids, right? And you want to
give them the best life possible. I love
being immersed in that type of crowd
because I feel the love, right? Yeah.
Yeah. Well, like, you know, we're, again,
it was so great that you and I had the
opportunity to meet in person when you're
out here and your big, your big family
road trip, right? And just that, afternoon
that we all got to spend together, the
families and that was really special for
everyone. mean, Stone still talks about it
and takes the pictures. That was.
Oh, and thank you for reminding me. got a
ton of pictures. haven't posted them yet.
Oh, okay. I need do that. Right. I need
that privilege of time, but that's the
reason why we flew the whole family from
Toronto over to Vancouver, went to
Bellingham and then went to Seattle and
back again. Right. We just love the
community out there. Every time I see you
guys advertising the, what is it? Beans
and boards. Oh my gosh. I'm like, I wish I
could be there. Right.
I can just imagine the love, the happiness
and joy that's going to be inside that
crowd. It's a wonderful thing, right?
Yeah, no, you're absolutely right. And
that
again, is another form of privilege too,
to have that opportunity. this is just a
message that I'm going to continue to beat
on this podcast because frankly, for so
long, I didn't have community when
Stone...
was young, there wasn't, there weren't
Facebook groups, there weren't a lot.
They've
come a long ways and it's just, so
valuable for mental health. And we know
that we,
need to have our mental health, right? We
need to be on our game to be there for our
kids, whether they're, whether they're
kids or whether they're young adults.
Yeah.
And so I just really encourage people to,
you know, reach out and find they're out
there now. We know that all over they're
out there virtually and, if not person,
try
to, try to do it yourself. Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely. When my son cracks a
smile...
It's a great day. I can feel it. I can
absolutely feel it. And so that's what I
want
to return back to him and anybody else out
there, right? That we meet. Well, Andrew,
like I said, we knew there's so much to
talk about. We're going to definitely have
to do part two. Part two, I want to talk
about the study a little bit more, let
people know about that. Cause I think
that's important. And the app again that
you
created and some other things, but you
know, that we'll have to wait.
for our next get together. But thank you
so much again for joining me. This has
been
awesome. Oh no, I thoroughly enjoyed it.
Thank you for the opportunity and look
forward to coming back again. Yeah, and
thank you audience members for joining us.
Catch us next time on the lighter side of
the spectrum.